<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present interest of England, or, A confutation of the Whiggish conspiratours anti-monyan principle shewing from reason and experience the ways to make the government safe, the king great, the people happy, money plentifull, and trade flourish.</title>
            <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16235</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280243</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 818:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present interest of England, or, A confutation of the Whiggish conspiratours anti-monyan principle shewing from reason and experience the ways to make the government safe, the king great, the people happy, money plentifull, and trade flourish.</title>
                  <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Dring ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Nalson. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: N.N.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Economics --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58680:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58680:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Preſent Intereſt OF ENGLAND; OR, A CONFUTATION OF THE Whiggiſh Conſpiratours Anti-Monyan Principle,</p>
            <p>SHEWING From <hi>REASON</hi> and <hi>EXPERIENCE</hi> The ways to make the GOVERNMENT Safe, The KING Great, The PEOPLE Happy, MONEY Plentifull, and TRADE Flouriſh.</p>
            <q>Omne tulit punctum —</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Dring,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Chancery-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58680:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58680:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF you are an honeſt Loyal Gentleman, and to ſuch I write, here are ſome things in the following Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, which I doubt not but you will judge to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Title, and the Preſent Intereſt of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> if ſo, you will doe your ſelf right, if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to promote the knowledge of it, to your Friends and Neighbours, the Price will not affright you, if you diſpatch one or two of them to your Country Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. It is not vanity of fooliſh Opinion in the performance, puts me upon this humour, but that once in our lives we may come even with the Factious Whiggiſh Conſpiratours, who have left no Corner of the Nation unpoiſoned with their <hi>Appeals,</hi> their <hi>Vox Populi's,</hi> their <hi>Growths of Popery,</hi> and whatever might help to ſubvert the Government. And if there can be any reaſon given, why we ſhould be leſs indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, conſidering what we muſt expect from them,
<pb facs="tcp:58680:3"/>ſhould they ever prevail, to ſupport the Government and ſecure our ſelves, I will be contented to be thought very impertinent, both in my Deſign, and the requeſt which is made by,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIR, Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>N. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58680:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Preſent Intereſt</hi> OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>IT is now almoſt a Century of years, ſince this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Glory of all Iſlands, the Miſtreſs of the Ocean, fitted by Nature, and the very complexion of its Martial, Sea-faring and numerous Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, if not for the Empire, yet to give Laws to the Peace and Traffick of the Univerſe, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> hath languiſhed under the waſting <hi>Hectick</hi> of its own inteſtine Diſorders, the miſerable Scars of our Civil Wounds, and unnatural as well as unreaſonable Diſſentions, are but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58680:4"/>ſtill too viſible marks of our paſt folly and preſent weakneſs. To what degrees of Glory and Reputation in the World, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Name and <hi>Nation</hi> might have been advanced, had thoſe Conquering Arms, that Valiant Blood, and thoſe Prodigious Treaſures, which were ſo prodigally expended in the late Rebellion, been employed for the Honour and Advantage of the Kingdom, it is almoſt impoſſible to make any near conjecture; but moſt aſſuredly <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> rendered themſelves Maſters of the Greateſt Empires of the Earth, at a far leſs Expence of Blood and Treaſure. A Conſideration, capable of tranſporting Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Spirits into an exceſs of Indignation, and the moſt juſt abhorrence of thoſe men and Principles, whoſe Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent and Ambitious Actions have robbed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at once of ſo much Glory abroad, Peace, Men and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney at home, as might have made the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Diadem ſhine among the moſt Illuſtrious of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> But what Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is able to ſupport the aſſaults of thoſe afflicting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, that whereas we might have rendered our ſelves the moſt potent, formidable, happy and flouriſhing People of the World, we have by our own madneſs and Civil Rage, not only leſſened our own Strength and Glory, but have at the ſame time and by the ſame ways advanced the Power, and dangerous Reputation of our Neighbours; who ſeem to owe whatever they poſſeſs that is Great or Formidable, more to our brutiſh and wretched Folly, to give it no worſe Character, then to their own Prudence, Conduct, or Extraordinary Policy; <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> who can now upon occaſion cover the Narrow Seas with Hoſtile Sails, muſt have been ſtill contented, as formerly, to beg Permiſſion for a few Fiſhing Boats to ſpread their toiling Canvaſs upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Main, had the tenth part of the Money which was conſumed in Rebellion been employed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58680:4"/>to maintain the <hi>Royal Prerogative</hi> of our Princes, and the juſt Dominion which they have in Right of their Imperial Crown, over the four Seas.</p>
            <p>It was a ſharp Obſervation which <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the <hi>Duc Rohan</hi> made concerning <hi>England,</hi> in his Book entituled <hi>Intereſt des Eſtates; Angleterre eſt un Grand Animal qui ne mourira jamais s'il neſe tue luy meſme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> is a great Animal which can never dye, unleſs ſhe Kill her ſelf.</note> By-ſtanders it ſeems will ever ſee more then Gameſters, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe one would think it impoſſible that this <hi>French Duke</hi> ſhould ſee at ſo remote a diſtance, what ſome of our <hi>Dukes, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> too, will not ſee, at the neareſt view, that if ever <hi>England</hi> periſh it muſt be by her own hands; but the truth is, they do ſee it too plainly, &amp; have therefore entertained thoſe hopes to ſatisfie their own ambition by the common ruin; and how deeply this <hi>Nation</hi> therefore ſtands indebted to thoſe People who have taken ſuch Immortal pains to Ruin it by inteſtine Wars, and to weaken it by continual Diſorders and Commotions within it ſelf, I think to our ſhame as well as irreparable dammage, is obvious to all the neighbouring World.</p>
            <p>We ſeem now to be upon the very turn of our Affairs, and there appears a promiſing <hi>Criſis,</hi> and favourable Proſpect of Recovery, and tho' it is at all times, yet more eſpecially in ſuch a conjuncture, certainly it is a Duty which every <hi>Engliſhman</hi> ows to God, his Prince and Country, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to promote the Peace and Happineſs, the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and Glory of his Native Soil; and he is unworthy to reap the advantages and priviledges, which the Subjects of this Kingdom Enjoy beyond any other in the World, under the moſt admirable Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws and Monarchy, who ſhall refuſe or neglect at ſuch a time to lend his utmoſt aſſiſtance to ſupport, maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58680:5"/>it, and to contribute what he can towards the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this <hi>Nation</hi> from its diſorders and diſtractions, to its priſtine State of Strength and Glory.</p>
            <p>Now the certain method for the Recovery of that true condition of health in the Body Politique, ſeems to depend upon our right underſtanding of what it is that hath hurt us, and what will help us. The laſt of theſe neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the knowledge of the firſt: For if we once knew from what Cauſes all our former miſchiefs have taken their Original, the removing thoſe Cauſes, will certainly ceaſe the dangerous Effects, and afford us an Eaſie as well as an undoubted Cure.</p>
            <p>Now there are two things upon which the rebellious <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Faction</hi> of the Nation to whom we are owing for all our Miſeries, have ever laid the whole ſtreſs &amp; weight of their wicked Deſigns, and from the good or ill ſucceſs of thoſe two great <hi>Engines,</hi> they have always ſtated the meaſures of their hopes. The firſt hath been to diſtreſs the Crown; the ſecond to diſtract and diſaffect the People. By the one they diveſt the <hi>King</hi> of thoſe neceſſary ſupports which ſhould enable him to keep up the Strength, Honor and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Government: And by the other they diſrobe him of the hearts, and affections of the People; and theſe being the two <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Throne,</hi> the ſhaking and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining of theſe, muſt needs make it totter, and be in danger of ſinking, both in its <hi>Intereſt</hi> abroad, and its <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> at home.</p>
            <p>I do not now write a bare ſuppoſition, but plain matter of <hi>Fact</hi> both theſe particulars; and ſuch matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> as hath in a thouſand diſmal Inſtances produced in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from theſe Cauſes the moſt deplorable Effects; Even the total Ruin of the whole Frame of the Government; the ſubverſion of the <hi>Monarchy;</hi> the overthrow of the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58680:5"/>
               <hi>Religion;</hi> the intire loſs of our <hi>Magna Charta, Engliſh</hi> Laws and Liberties; the ſolemn Murther of a moſt Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, juſt, wiſe, and Excellent <hi>King;</hi> the ſlaughter of many thouſands of <hi>Loyal Subjects</hi> of all degrees; the baniſhment or impriſonment of others; the Sacrilegious Robbing and irreligious defacing of Churches, thoſe Monuments of Piety &amp; Antiquity; the Confiſcations, plundering, Arbitrary Taxing, and Spoiling of the Free-born <hi>People</hi> of their Legal Property in their Goods and Eſtates, to ſuch degrees as ſurpaſſeth the skill of the ableſt Accomptants to make a true Eſtimate of; and were it poſſible to ſtate the accompt, and take a perfect audit of all the Expences in the late wicked <hi>Rebellion,</hi> the incredible Summs then profuſely waſted, would not only Exceed belief, but every thing, except the Crimes of thoſes men, who were the black contrivers of the occaſion of thoſe Expences, and that irreparable Damage of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and if, as 'tis uſually obſerved, the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> be ſuch lovers of their Money and their Liberty, one would think, they might here find ſufficient reaſon to deteſt and abhor theſe Factious men and Principles, who have once robbed them of both theſe, and have offered ſo fair to do it a ſecond time; &amp; be ſo wiſe for the future as never to ſuffer themſelves to be impoſed upon, by ſuch notorious Impoſtors and Pretences; and that they may be enabled to do ſo, it is to be obſerved,</p>
            <p>That in order to the accompliſhment of the firſt of theſe Deſigns, the Diſtreſſing of the <hi>Crown,</hi> the continual Addreſs and Labour of the <hi>Faction</hi> hath been employed in theſe two things; firſt to ſhorten the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and clip the wings of it in all its ſeveral Branches; Secondly, Either to deny thoſe legal Aids of Money, by Subſidies and other wayes abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to ſupport the Charges of the Government; or to give them ſo ſparingly, as not to anſwer the unavoidable Expences of the <hi>Crown;</hi> and this too, out of pretended good Husbandry and Frugality for the <hi>Nation,</hi> and with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58680:6"/>quarrelling at the publique <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and Eternal Complaints of the miſ-mannagement of the Treaſure: when as in truth, the real deſign of this popular <hi>Parſimony,</hi> was to keep the <hi>Prince's Exchequer</hi> at low water mark; and to have opportunity to barter with him for ſome part of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and for every penny granted, ſtill to have ſome <hi>Jewel</hi> or other out of the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My narrow limits will not allow me to deſcend to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, but whoever doubts the truth of this, let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our Hiſtories, and they will preſently receive ſatisfaction, that ſince the Reign of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> in whoſe latter years the <hi>Faction</hi> began to appear numerous &amp; troubleſome, the <hi>Prerogative</hi> has conſtantly diminiſhed in proportion as the power and confidence of the turbulent <hi>Faction</hi> hath been augmented, inſomuch that that <hi>Queen</hi> in the 35th year of her Reign, <hi>Anno</hi> 1592. ſent Mr. <hi>Peter Wentworth</hi> an Sir <hi>Henry Bromely</hi> to the <hi>Tower,</hi> where <hi>Wentworth</hi> dyed, only for delivering a Petition to the Lord <hi>Keeper,</hi> deſiring the Lords to become Suppliants with them of the Lower Houſe, unto Her <hi>Majeſty</hi> for Entailing the Succeſſion of the Crown, for which purpoſe there was a Bill ready drawn, and <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> did not then ſo much as once openly murmur againſt <hi>Prerogative;</hi> whereas, when <hi>King Charles</hi> the Firſt, upon an Impeachment of High Treaſon, came in perſon, and demanded Five Members of the Commons Houſe; the whole <hi>Nation</hi> was put into as great a flame, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion, with the Intrenching of <hi>Prerogative</hi> upon. <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> as if the <hi>King</hi> had come with <hi>Fauxes</hi> dark Lanthorn, to give Fire to a Mine which ſhould have blown up that and all future <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though the Enemies of the <hi>Monarchy</hi> endeavoured to leſſen the Power of the Crown in this particular of <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative,</hi> yet this was nothing ſo dangerous as the withdrawing neceſſary Supplies of money: For Treaſure is the very Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58680:6"/>Spirit of the Government, and according to the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which it enjoyes of that active metal, the Pulſe of the Government will certainly beat either full and ſtrong, or weak and languiſhing. <hi>Sine vectigalibus nullum Imperium diu ſubſiſtere poteſt,</hi> ſaith the Politick Hiſtorian. And this the Bleſſed Son of God himſelf hath confirmed both by his Doctrine and Practice; for tho' his <hi>Kingdom</hi> was not of this World, yet he ſo well underſtood that the Government of the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this World were to be ſupported by Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and was ſo ſenſible of the neceſſity of Government, for the common benefit of Mankind, and that this Common benefit ought to be ſupported at a Common charge, that for our Example, he would not Exempt himſelf from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tribute, but wrought a <hi>Miracle</hi> to furniſh his <hi>Quota</hi> of the Tax impoſed upon his <hi>Nation,</hi> that ſo he might contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute his proportion to the maintaining of the Government, and this tho' our <hi>Antimonarchical Demogogues</hi> know ſo well, yet notwithſtanding his poſitive Precept to <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> he muſt work a greater Miracle to perſuade them to comply with their Duty, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; and if there were no better <hi>Chriſtians</hi> or Subjects then the men of the <hi>Faction,</hi> notwithſtanding this indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſible Law and Precept, the more obedient Fiſhes muſt bring their <hi>Miraclous Tribute</hi> and Subſidies to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or elſe the Crown muſt ſtarve and Fall, or which is worſe fall into their uſurping hands.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s infamous Speech to this purpoſe, is ſtill freſh in all mens memories, and indeed I think it was ſo good a peice of Service, in diſcovering the great Secret and the Deſign of the <hi>Faction,</hi> that it ought never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; <hi>If you part with your Money,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Nation is betrayed.</hi> From whence it is Evident, what ſtreſs his Lordſhip, who was then the <hi>Oraculous</hi> Mouth of the <hi>Faction,</hi> laid upon this matter of Supplies, and granting money to the <hi>King.</hi> For
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58680:7"/>he and the next of his fellow <hi>Inſpirators,</hi> as is ſince diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and was then by all knowing and honeſt men juſtly ſuſpected, were then buſily complotting, with Security to themſelves how to overthrow this moſt admirable and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and this they took to be the moſt certain Expedient to effect it. It is probable that at that time he and his Aſſociates were not advanced to thoſe infatuated de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and methods of deſperation and madneſs, to which the blaſting of their Hopes and Deſigns by the Breath of Heaven and its <hi>Miraculous Providences,</hi> did afterwards tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport them; the <hi>Debate</hi> was, how to Eſcape the odious Character of <hi>Rebels,</hi> and yet decently to deſtroy the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by taking off the Wheels from the Chariot of State; and for this purpoſe nothing appears it ſeems ſo conducive as <hi>No Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſingular in his Judgment, the whole Body of the <hi>Faction</hi> in their ſmart Adreſſes to the <hi>Patriots</hi> of their Party, collected into a <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> or <hi>Vox Patriae,</hi> ſung the very ſame note, and were all ſet to the ſame Tune of <hi>Without ever a penny of Money;</hi> and at the ſame inſtant that they were ſo profuſe of their promiſes to their popular <hi>Tribunes,</hi> to aſſiſt and ſtand by them with their Lives and Fortunes, yet the ſting in the Tayl of the little <hi>Cockatrices</hi> vvas ſtill, <hi>Not to part with any Money,</hi> or at leaſt not vvithout good Security, the Mortgaging of the Crown Jewels to the <hi>Faction,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> if he would have any money, tho' they knew <hi>Tangier</hi> ready to be loſt, and made the <hi>Nation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>French Philiſtims</hi> were upon them, yet muſt pawn the <hi>Militia,</hi> Forts, Magazines, Navy, for their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, all which muſt be put into the hands of the principal men of the <hi>Faction,</hi> who were to be the <hi>Royal Pawn-Brokers,</hi> or elſe <hi>No Money:</hi> Nay this would not ſatisfie them neither, the <hi>King</hi> muſt alſo, by a <hi>Bill of Excluſion</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58680:7"/>ſacrifice, not only, his <hi>only Brother,</hi> but the very ſucceſſion in a lineal and hereditary deſcent, and by conſequence the <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf, otherwiſe, <hi>Not one peny of mony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay ſo eagerly was the <hi>Faction</hi> ſet upon this, <hi>No Mony</hi> Expedient, and at this mark were all their hopes of ſucceſs in their wicked Deſigns ſo fixed; that they became reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute not only, not to grant the <hi>King</hi> any ſupplies of mony except upon theſe terms, but leſt he ſhould be able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt for the preſent without it, and by advancing Mony up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Reputation and Credit of his Eſtabliſhed Revenue, preſerve <hi>Tangier</hi> then in imminent danger of being loſt, and and ſupport the Government, the inraged <hi>Faction,</hi> that they might do their utmoſt to reduce the Crown to the laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities raiſed thoſe tempeſtuous Votes of <hi>Jan.</hi> 7. 1680.</p>
            <p>Reſolved, &amp;c. <hi>That whoſoever ſhall hereafter lend or cauſe to be lent by way of advance, any Mony upon the Branches of the Kings Revenue ariſing by Cuſtoms, Exciſe, Hearth-mony, ſhall be adjudged to hinder the ſitting of Parliaments, and ſhall be reſponſible for the ſame in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolved, &amp;c. <hi>That whoſoever ſhall accept, or buy any Tally of Anticipation upon any part of the Kings Revenue, or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall pay ſuch Tally, hereafter to be ſtruck, ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged to hinder the ſitting of Parliaments, and ſhall be reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible therefore in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was then become a terrible thing to be Voted a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of the ſitting of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and to be reſponſible in <hi>Parliament;</hi> for the next Vote was to brand them for Favourers of <hi>Popery,</hi> and Enemies to the <hi>King</hi> and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, with which Characters they ſtigmatized the Lords <hi>Halifax, Clarendon,</hi> and <hi>Feverſham,</hi> and the now Earl of <hi>Rocheſter;</hi> for adhering to the <hi>King,</hi> and oppoſing the <hi>Faction,</hi> and doubtleſs could a <hi>Vote</hi> have made it Capital and <hi>high Treaſon</hi> for any perſon to lend mony by way of Anticipation, they would have proceeded to that too.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58680:8"/>
            <p>And the practice hath held an exact conformity to the Principle upon which it is grounded; for not one ſingle Farthing hath been granted to the Crown, ſince this <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury-Commonwealths-men</hi> have had any manner of power to hinder it. By all which it doth moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, that the ſubverting of the Government which was intended, was to have been effected, by bringing the Crown into the utmoſt neceſſity and diſtreſs, that the <hi>King</hi> might not have a penny to help himſelf withall, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently be forced into thoſe compliances, deſtructive to the very Eſſence of the <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, in regard it muſt appear, even to the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different apprehenſions, moſt undutiful, unnatural and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable for the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the People, to treat the Father of their Country, their natural liege Lord and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign at this unkind rate; therefore the ſecond <hi>Engine</hi> of diſtracting the People, and alienating their Hearts and Affections from the <hi>King,</hi> is next to come in play, and to be advanced as the Reaſon of the former. It would appear barbarous, and lay the Deſign too open and bare faced, to deny ſupplies neceſſary for the ſupport of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to be able to give no Reaſon for it; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impoſſible there ſhould be any true Reaſon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, therefore that defect is to be ſupplied by ſuch Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Reaſons, as may recompence what they want of truth, by their being plauſible, fair and popular. For this is moſt certain, that there are ſome things which the <hi>Populace</hi> will always believe to be true, though they are never ſo falſe. And there are ſome things which the Popular Ringleaders of <hi>Faction,</hi> know to be moſt falſe, yet becauſe they are apt to be credited by the Jealous Multitude, they induſtriouſly endeavour to impoſe them upon them as the greateſt Truths. As for Example, the <hi>People</hi> are always eaſily perſuaded that they labour under real Grievances, though they be never ſo imaginary; and then again they are apt as readily to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58680:8"/>that theſe pretended Popular <hi>Patriots,</hi> will, as they conſtantly pretend, really redreſs thoſe Imaginary Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. The <hi>Faction</hi> conſtantly accuſe the Government of Miſcarriages in the management of publick affairs, and though nothing be more falſe, yet the People will believe the accuſation. A more pregnant Inſtance of which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be given then in the Caſe of <hi>Ship-mony.</hi> This was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as the moſt intolerable Grievance and illegal Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon the People, though all the <hi>Judges,</hi> except two, gave their Opinions for the legality of it. But ſo was the matter managed and improved by the popular Men of the <hi>Faction,</hi> that the whole <hi>Nation</hi> ſeemed to groan under the burthen as a moſt inſupportable Grievance; the great Sticklers <hi>Pym, Hambden, Strode,</hi> &amp;c. ingratiate themſelves by oppoſing it, and inflame the People againſt the <hi>King</hi> and Government for impoſing it. The <hi>King</hi> upon their Remonſtrating and Importunities takes it quite away by Act of <hi>Parliament.</hi> But what was the event? Did theſe <hi>Patriots</hi> eaſe the People ever a whit the more? No ſuch matter; their Deſign was to leſſen the Crown not to Eaſe, the People. For did they not invite the Rebellious <hi>Scots</hi> to invade the Nation, which coſt the People above a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of Mony? And after they had accompliſhed their own deſign in cutting of ſuch a limb of <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and by other ways ſo weakned the <hi>King,</hi> as that they durſt, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to grapple with him in Rebellion in the open field, they thought no longer of Redreſſing the Grievances, or eaſing the People of illegal Impoſitions, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, laid ſuch intolerable Impoſitions and Arbitrary Taxes upon the People, as had not the leaſt colour of legality to countenance and ſupport them; inſomuch that for 300000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> which was the utmoſt that ever the <hi>Ship-mony</hi> was computed to amount to, they levied by Taxes, Exciſe, Publick Faith, Contributions, Sequeſtrations, Free quarter and plunder, a large ſum, above ſo many Millions in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58680:9"/>year, and yet then the ſtupid People could not be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to believe, but that their <hi>Arbitrary Tyrants</hi> and Illegal Oppreſſors were their great Friends, and their lawful <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Ministers</hi> their greateſt Enemies; and though the <hi>Faction</hi> exerciſed actually that <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> which they only accuſed the <hi>King</hi> with deſigning, yet the beſotted People would ſtill believe them innocent and ſuſpect the <hi>King</hi> to be guilty.</p>
            <p>There are two things, of which all mankind are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally moſt infinitely tender, the <hi>Liberty</hi> of their Perſons, and the <hi>Property</hi> of their Eſtates; and a third which all men pretend to be wonderfully Zealous for, and that is their <hi>Religion;</hi> though of late we have ſeen, that they who have the leaſt ſhare of it and by their Actions the leaſt value for it, have made the moſt noiſe and clamour about the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of loſing it; and in probability they did ſo too in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; but theſe are three things, which the <hi>Faction</hi> have conſtantly endeavoured to poſſeſs the People with a belief, that they were in the utmoſt danger of loſing, and that this danger proceeded from the ill Deſigns which the Government had againſt them; and further, that if the worthy Patriots of the <hi>Faction</hi> had not oppoſed the Court, <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> had long ſince robbed the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of whatever is moſt valuable in this world. And it is incredible, not only, what Art and Induſtry hath been uſed to infuſe this intoxicating Poiſon into the heads of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, thereby to inſpire them with Fears, Jealouſies and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Government, and to countenance the denial of Supplies, which the People were made believe by the men of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> if granted, was but to contribute towards betraying their own Intereſt and Liberty, and to enable the <hi>King</hi> and Government to impoſe upon them and their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity the Shackles and Manacles of future <hi>ſlavery;</hi> but is alſo moſt wonderful, what ſucceſs the ſtrong impreſſions of theſe Forgeries, Falſhoods and Calumnies have had amongſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58680:9"/>the People. All the Tongues and the moſt virulent Pens of the <hi>Faction,</hi> have for this forty years and upwards been continually employed in creating and infuſing theſe <hi>Fears and Jealouſies</hi> into the heads of the People; and in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving them, to raiſe in the People a diſtruſt, diſlike and hatred againſt the <hi>King</hi> and Government. This was the very <hi>method</hi> by which the late wicked <hi>Rebels</hi> debauched the minds of the People, and withdrew them from their Affection, Loyalty, Duty and Allegiance to the <hi>King,</hi> and having once prevailed with them to cancel thoſe obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they bewitched them ſtill with new, or repeated Fears and Jealouſies, into a moſt execrable <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which was carried on by all the ſteps of Cruelty, Injuſtice and Tyranny, and conſummated in the utter overthrow of the Eſtabliſhed Government, the deſtruction of the Church, the ſubverſion of the Crown, and the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and barbarous cutting off the Sacred Head that wore it.</p>
            <p>And how far the modern <hi>Conſpirators</hi> proceeded, and advanced by the very ſame ſteps, towards the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the late damnable <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> there are as many Witneſſes, as Subjects in the <hi>Nation</hi> who have taken any notice of the actions of the <hi>Faction,</hi> which will therefore ſuperſede the trouble of recounting: Let it ſuffice to ſay in ſhort, that there hath nothing been left unſaid, unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, unprinted, or undone from the <hi>Right Honourable and Right Worſhipful,</hi> to the meaneſt <hi>Whifflers</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> From the <hi>Lord Shaftsbury</hi> with his Speech of a <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> to pitiful <hi>Care, Curtis, Smith</hi> and <hi>Harris</hi> with their Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, Appeals, Intelligences and <hi>Vox Populis,</hi> from the very <hi>Parliament</hi> Houſe, down to the <hi>Coffee</hi>-houſe, from the <hi>City</hi> to the <hi>Country,</hi> from the ſpawning and licentious <hi>Preſs,</hi> the Conventicle <hi>Pulpit,</hi> down even to the ſcolding blew Apron <hi>Rethorick,</hi> which might be any ways thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive towards incenſing the People of all Ranks and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58680:10"/>in the Nation againſt the <hi>King</hi> and the Government, and to puſh them headlong into a ſecond <hi>Rebellion:</hi> And when all theſe ways failed, the Ring-leaders of the <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> driven on by the Fury of their ill <hi>Deſtiny,</hi> betook themſelves to the deſperate Refuge of raiſing Inſurrections, and that moſt Execrable deſign of Aſſaſſination of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Duke,</hi> and all thoſe who had in any meaſure rendred themſelves conſpicuous for their <hi>Loyalty</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Attempts of the <hi>Faction,</hi> and adhering to the Crown and Government in their diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>By this time it is eaſie to ſee, what it is that hath hurt us, and it will then be no difficult matter to tell what it is that will help us; For if theſe unreaſonable. Fears and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies for our Liberty, Property and Religion, and the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of neceſſary ſupplies of Mony to the <hi>Crown,</hi> have been the Occaſions of all thoſe Diſturbances and Dangers which have for theſe late years diſtracted this <hi>Nation;</hi> then by undeniable conſequence, the taking off thoſe Weights will immediately ſurceaſe thoſe violent motions, which have ſo diſordered our affairs, and reſtore Tranquility, Peace and Happineſs to the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the difficulty reſts in perſuading the People to make uſe of theſe <hi>Expedients,</hi> for though they may be convinced of the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of the <hi>Medicine,</hi> yet it is not without difficulty that they are to be induced to take <hi>Phyſick.</hi> Eſpecially this opening of the <hi>Mony Vein,</hi> makes them ſhrink, as much as if they were to part with as many drops of blood, as they are to drop pence. I cannot tell what effect the <hi>Experiment</hi> will have, but I will endeavour to try if I can make it appear to be the true <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> firſt to damm the ſluice of theſe Fears and Jealouſies, and ſecondly to ſet open the Mony Gate, and let in a Freſh Spring into the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, the exploding and for ever baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe deſtructive Jealouſies, and diſturbing Fears of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58680:10"/>danger of Innovation in <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſetting up of <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government</hi> in the State, I will not ſpin out a long and tedious diſcourſe upon any of the Common <hi>Topiques,</hi> made uſe of upon this ſubject, but I will tell the Reader a ſtory, which if well applied will give a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to any other Arguments.</p>
            <p>When at the beginning of the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> there were ſome overtures of an accommodation to the King at <hi>Oxon;</hi> the City of <hi>London</hi> ſent a Petition by ſome of their Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who being admitted into the Preſence; Alderman <hi>Garret</hi> undertook to be then Speaker, and told the <hi>King,</hi> that his Majeſty had many times promiſed to ſecure their Religion, Laws and Liberties, and Sir, ſaid he, could we but be ſecure and aſſured that you would do ſo, we would ſoon make an end of the buſineſs. At this pretty confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the <hi>Aldermans,</hi> the whole Court had much to do to forbear laughing outright; but the <hi>King</hi> according to the accuſtomed goodneſs of his Nature, with a gracious ſmile only, made him this mild reply, Mr. <hi>Alderman, I know not how to make you confide in me, but you ſhall do well to believe thoſe that lie leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to apply this paſſage, I will beg the Readers Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to enquire into theſe particulars, and to examine who have ſpoke the greateſt truth, the <hi>Kings</hi> in their repeated promiſes, to ſecure our Religion, Properties and Laws; or the <hi>Faction</hi> who have made ſuch extraordinary promiſes to the <hi>Nation</hi> in all theſe particulars; and have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by aſſuming to themſelves all the glory of ſecuring our Religion, Laws and Liberties, moſt invidiouſly to caſt an <hi>Odium</hi> upon the Crown, as intending to divert the People of them.</p>
            <p>I do therefore in the firſt place peremptorily challenge the whole <hi>Faction</hi> to give one ſingle Inſtance, during the whole Reigns of <hi>King James, King Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> or his Illuſtrious Son our preſent Sovereign <hi>King Charles</hi> the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58680:11"/>Second, wherein any mans Property to particulars or that of the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> in general, hath been contrary to the known Laws of the Land invaded; or to ſhew wherein the <hi>Monarchical</hi> Conſtitution hath governed Arbitrarily: What life hath been taken away except in the juſt defenſive War againſt the Rebels, but according to the known Laws of the Land? Who hath been outlawed or baniſhed, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeized of his Freehold, impriſoned, or any other ways damnified by the <hi>Kings</hi> or their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but <hi>per legale Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium Parium,</hi> by the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> and by the Verdict of their Peers? What mony hath been raiſed but by legal and <hi>Parliamentary</hi> ways? What Force of armed. Men hath been made uſe of to overawe the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> how much neceſſity ſoever there hath appeared of more then ordinary Force, both againſt Foreign dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and inteſtine <hi>Rebels?</hi> Certainly if there could have been found any Inſtances of this nature, we ſhould have had them ſoundly repeated in the Ears of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and every man of the <hi>Faction</hi> would have been a <hi>Trumpeter</hi> to proclaim them;. for it is a <hi>maxim</hi> with them never to conceal any Action that may redound to the diſparagement of the Government, and rather to create falſhoods, where they fall ſhort of truth.</p>
            <p>And for want of particular Inſtances wherewith to charge the Government, and fortifie their Calumnies, the <hi>Faction</hi> have always been ſo well aware, that in all their Clamorous and moſt virulent <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> which have been ſtuffed out with ſo many bitter Invectives againſt the Government upon this <hi>Topique</hi> of Slavery and Arbitrary Power breaking in upon the <hi>Nation,</hi> they have either charged the Government with Deſign and Intention only, or elſe with Generals only; cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly foreſeeing, that if they had deſcended to give parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Inſtances, they muſt have betrayed the weakneſs as well as falſeneſs of their accuſation, and have expoſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58680:11"/>themſelves and Cauſe to the View of the whole World as guilty of Forgery and Impoſture: and the two moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable <hi>Pamphlets</hi> of this kind, intituled the <hi>firſt and ſecond Part of the Growth of Popery and Arbitrary Government;</hi> the one written by <hi>Marvel,</hi> ſometime one of <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi>'s Latin Secretaries; and die other, by that notorious Traitor <hi>Ferguſon,</hi> the <hi>Independent</hi> Tubſter, the moſt daring and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious of any thing of that Nature; yet have ſtrictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this Rule, and have therefore indeavoured to impoſe upon the Credulous, or thoſe that were willing to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, by charging the Government with Generals, and wreſting the moſt innocent Actions and Words of the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> to make them depoſe ſome extorted Sence, tending towards introducing of <hi>Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> but from the one End to the other, more cautiouſly then honeſtly, avoiding the giving any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtances wherein the <hi>King,</hi> or his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> have actually exceeded the Limits of the Laws: Which is a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration</hi> as clear as the Meridian Sun, that they durſt not adventure at what they knew there was no poſſibility of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and conſequently, that the Government is clear and innocent of what they accuſe it.</p>
            <p>But now on the other hand, notwithſtanding all the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Outcries againſt the Government, and all the ſmooth Pretenſions which the <hi>Commonwealth Faction</hi> have made of ſecuring the <hi>Nation</hi> againſt <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> and <hi>Slavery;</hi> there is not any one Branch of Liberty and Property which they have not violated; and wherein there may not be a thouſand diſmal Inſtances given of their Exerciſing the moſt illegal, tyrannical, and exquiſitely <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> over the Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, not only of ſome particular Perſons, their Enemies or Oppoſers, but of the whole <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Scottiſh,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Nations:</hi> Volumes will not contain the Murders, Rapines, Oppreſſions, Sequeſtrations, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimations, Impriſonments, and what ever can be thought of, that was Cruel, illegal, Unjuſt, or <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> which were exerciſed promiſcuouſly over their Friends and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58680:12"/>by thoſe Perſons to whom the Gracious <hi>Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion</hi> was granted at his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s happy Reſtauration. And who were theſe <hi>Arbitrary Tyrants,</hi> but thoſe who complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the danger of that <hi>Bugbear</hi> from the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> who fought with the <hi>King</hi> to ſecure the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, as they pretended; and who ſo often promiſed the People to eaſe them of their Grievances, and defend their Liberties and Properties? but the Liberty ended in the moſt abſolute Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very: Nay, I do poſitively averr, that the <hi>Slavery</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> under this uſurping Republican <hi>Faction,</hi> was in ſome meaſure greater then that which is exerciſed by the <hi>Turkiſh Sultan;</hi> for where he Conquers, he leaves the Vanquiſhed at intire Liberty to keep their <hi>Religion:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as when theſe <hi>Engliſh Turks</hi> had gotten the Victory over the <hi>King</hi> and the Royal Party; though they tolerated all Sects, Hereſies, and Schiſmaticks, yet ſo far as they could, they made it Unlawful and Criminal for the Loyal Subjects, to Exerciſe, even that <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> which by Laws unrepealed, and the moſt ſolemn Oaths, from which they could not be, by any Power whatever, diſpenſed with, they were bound to perform: So that they had no Choice left, but Perjury or Puniſhment. For during all the time of the late Uſurpation, the whole Body of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> many of thoſe who were the forwardeſt, even from the Pulpit to promote Rebellion, ſuch as <hi>Barges, Marſhal, Nye, Caſe,</hi> &amp;c. were under the Obligation of their own voluntary Oaths of Supremacy and Canonical Obedience to their Ordinaries the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> as ſupreme Head and Governour of the Church, and to his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Laws; and the whole Body of the Laiety of the <hi>Nation</hi> were obliged by the Act of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> for Uniformity and all thoſe other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes made during hers, and the Reign of <hi>King James</hi> for maintaining <hi>Epiſcopal Proteſtancy,</hi> both againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> which then, and to this preſent Day, ſtand unrepealed: Inſomuch, that by obliging the whole <hi>Nation</hi> to take the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to Swear and Vow the utter Extirpation of <hi>Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58680:12"/>the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and all the Ceremonies of Divine worſhip, which were eſtabliſhed by Law, and ſecured by moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oaths, they neceſſarily and unavoidably forced the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into a manifeſt and damnable <hi>Perjury</hi> on the one hand or the other: For if they took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled all Men, ſo far as they were able, to do, all thoſe who indeavoured the Extirpation of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> were guilty of the Breach of the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and if they did not indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it, they were by their <hi>Covenant</hi> perjured and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn. So that here was <hi>Arbitrary Tyranny</hi> with a Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, not only over the Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates; but over the Souls and <hi>Conſciences</hi> of the People of theſe three <hi>Nations</hi> in general; ſuch an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> as the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf could not have exceeded, unleſs in that downright Traiterous and Damnable <hi>Engagement,</hi> which they afterwards impoſed, point blank contrary to the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> their <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> too, for maintaining the Priviledges of <hi>Parliament,</hi> by which they obliged the Takers, <hi>To be true to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it was then Eſtabliſhed without a King and Houſe of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for their great pretence of ſecuring the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> againſt <hi>Popery;</hi> what Advantage could that be to the People, after they had done their uttermoſt Indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to Damn them Eternally, by an Univerſal <hi>Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi> For my part I can ſee very little difference in the Caſe, whether a Man goes to the <hi>Devil</hi> for <hi>Perjury</hi> or <hi>Popery,</hi> and I believe ſuch of them as have tried, will find it comes all to a Reckoning. But after all the Noiſe, I do not find upon the matter that the <hi>Nation</hi> was ever a whit the more ſecured from <hi>Popery,</hi> but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that <hi>Popiſh Principles</hi> every where gained ground upon the <hi>Nation,</hi> and that <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in the Dreſs of the ſeveral Sects were as buſie as ever, and that by the very force of the Argument of our Diviſions, and by the kind uſage of thoſe who were driven into Exile by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58680:13"/>theſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> they made more <hi>Proſelytes</hi> in twenty Years, then they had done in a Hundred before. It was a very notable Obſervation of <hi>Dr. Laud,</hi> the ſuffering Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in his Speech upon the Scaffold in the Year 1644. <hi>I pray God,</hi> (ſaid that admirable <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> who as he there tells us, loſt his Head upon the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Clamour of <hi>Venient Romani,</hi>) <hi>this Clamor of</hi> Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Romani, <hi>of which I have given no Cauſe, haſten not to bring them in; for the Pope never had ſuch a Harveſt in</hi> England <hi>ſince the Reformation, as he hath now upon the Sects and Diviſions that are among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after all, what did it ſignifie to keep out one <hi>Great Pope,</hi> and let in a thouſand little ones? juſt as much as if <hi>Belzebub</hi> had been caſt out, and the whole Legion of leſſer <hi>Devils</hi> left behind in him that was poſſeſſed. For the plain Truth is, they kept out the <hi>Pope,</hi> but kept in <hi>Popery,</hi> the rankeſt and moſt miſchievous Doctrines and Practices of the worſt of Men of that Religion. What <hi>Mariana, Allen, Suarez,</hi> and other traiterous <hi>Jeſuits</hi> had writ concerning the Depoſing and Murdering of Princes, they Aced; and from theſe Authors, they borrowed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to juſtifie their <hi>Rebellion</hi> and the blackeſt of Crimes. And whereas the <hi>Papacy</hi> was by ſo many Laws driven out of <hi>England</hi> for Errors in Doctrine, for Sedition, Rebellion, and Treaſon againſt the <hi>Monarchy</hi> and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Principles and Practices, there was not one Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or Hereſie in all the <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> which was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable by the Laws, but what was put in practice by theſe <hi>Pope-Haters.</hi> And for the other Errors of a lower Form, what was wanting of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Purgatory, Maſſes, Prayers to the Saints, &amp;c.</hi> was abundantly ſupplied by ten thouſand other Errors and Hereſies, which were held, maintained, and propagated by the ſeveral <hi>Sects</hi> which were tolerated by them, under the notion of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for <hi>Tender Conſciences;</hi> and ſuch Errors as were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive, not only of the Reformed, but of all manner of <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi> Such as denying <hi>the Articles of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58680:13"/>Creed;</hi> the <hi>Divinity of Chriſt;</hi> the Validity and Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> the Obligation of the <hi>Moral Law;</hi> the Immortality of the Soul; the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body;</hi> the Lawfulneſs of an Oath; the Neceſſity of a <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> or <hi>Sacraments;</hi> the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable others which were held and maintained by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and preached to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded People for ſaving Truths, whereas they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt damnable Hereſies. Thus did they ſecure the Nation from <hi>Popery,</hi> and kept out the <hi>Whore of Babylon,</hi> by letting in the <hi>Devil of Babel,</hi> and letting open a hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gates to Hell under pretence of ſtopping up one.</p>
            <p>Let the beſt Manager of the <hi>Faction</hi> now ſhew us, where the Government hath ſince the firſt of <hi>Queen Eliz.</hi> made one ſingle ſtep towards a return to <hi>Rome,</hi> or to any other of thoſe damnable Errors and Hereſies, which are every whit as dangerous to the Peace and Quiet of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and to the well-being and happineſs of both the Souls, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and Societies of Mankind.</p>
            <p>So that, now to come to my Story again; ſince it doth plainly appear in Fact, that the <hi>King</hi> and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have never deceived us in their Promiſes, to ſecure us againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> and that on the other ſide, the <hi>Faction,</hi> notwithſtanding all their fair Pretences and repeated <hi>Covenants, Engagements, Vows, Protestations,</hi> and <hi>Promiſes,</hi> have broken with us in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe particulars, a thouſand, and a thouſand times over; we muſt be not only moſt ſtupidly beſotted, but infatuated and bewitched, if either we believe ſuch notorious Deceivers any longer, or if for the future we do not repoſe an abſolute and intire Confidence, in the Goodneſs, and Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Honour of the <hi>King</hi> and Government, when they give us ſuch repeated Aſſurances, and ſuch undeniable <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> that they will protect us in the Enjoyment of our Laws, Liberties, Properties, and Religion.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58680:14"/>
            <p>And if we could once get clear of ibis <hi>Rub,</hi> which the <hi>Faction</hi> have always thrown as a ſtumbling Block in the Peoples Way, we ſhould with leſs difficulty get o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſecond. For if the <hi>Nation,</hi> as the wiſe Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaid, were but aſſured and ſecure, and that they may be as much as of any thing in this World, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Protection of the Government they ſhould enjoy their Laws, Liberty and Religion, they would then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, for their own Sakes, be not only willing, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſupply the <hi>Crown</hi> with Mony, not only in a bare proportion to the neceſſity of the Charges which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly attend the Government, but alſo to provide ſuch certain Supports, as might ſecure the <hi>Crown</hi> againſt any incident and unforeſeen Accidents, and maintain the Honor and Dignity of it, ſo as to make it ſit eaſie upon the <hi>Royal Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is certainly the Duty as well as Intereſt of the People, his <hi>Majeſties</hi> loving Subjects of all degrees of this <hi>Nation;</hi> for it is the higheſt Reaſon and Juſtice in the World, that a common and univerſal Good and Benefit, ſhould be promoted and advanced at a common Charge: and if it be every Mans Duty and Intereſt, as undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is, both by the Laws of God and Nature, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that Government under the Protection whereof he enjoys all: It is as certainly every Mans Duty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſuch a Proportion of his Eſtate, as may enable the Government to give him Protection. And we ſhould learn this Wiſdom from the Enemies of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that if the moſt certain and expeditious way to ruine and deſtroy it, be to withdraw the neceſſary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; then on the contrary, the moſt certain way to preſerve it, is for the Nation generouſly, and in a due proportion to the Charges of the Government to ſupply the <hi>Crown</hi> and recruit the <hi>Exchequer.</hi> And ſince it is moſt evident that they were the mortal Enemies of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> in this late <hi>Helliſh Plot,</hi> who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58680:14"/>by their Councels and Indeavours hindred the granting of Supplies, it is to be hoped, that hereafter, no Perſons will oppoſe it, who have hot a mind to be eſteemed ſo too, and to be ſuſpected to be influenced by thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Deſigns.</p>
            <p>I know it will preſently be objected, that the <hi>Nation</hi> is poor, and the Countries unable to raiſe Mony.</p>
            <p>To this, I ſhall, it may be, give a very uncommon Anſwer, when I reply, that one, and poſſibly one of the greateſt Reaſons and Occaſions of the Scarcity of Mony in the Country, is the not granting ſupplies of Mony to the <hi>Crown.</hi> And how much ſoever a <hi>Paradox</hi> this may at firſt view appear to be; it may be, upon ſecond thoughts, it may be found to be true; however, I will fairly leave it to the ſevere Conſideration of the moſt Judicious, and the ſtricteſt Examination of the moſt Scrupulous. If it be true, let it be allowed and cheriſhed, if it be falſe, let it be firſt refuted, and then rejected.</p>
            <p>I firſt then take it for granted, that the preſent ſcarcity of Mony in the Country, does not ariſe from the real de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Coin <hi>in ſpecie:</hi> and on the contrary, that there never was greater plenty of Coin, it appears moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently from the notable fall of <hi>Intereſt;</hi> for the Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the taking of <hi>Six per Cent.</hi> but four and a half, or five, is as much as is generally given, and it is incredible, upon good and ſound Security, what Sums may be had at four <hi>per Cent.</hi> and what Catching there is by the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veners,</hi> and <hi>Mony-Brokers</hi> at ſuch Cuſtomers, eſpecially now ſince the <hi>Bankers</hi> have declined in their Reputation. Now nothing in the world can be a greater <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of the Plenty of money, then this falling of <hi>Intereſt;</hi> and it is plain by many other Projects, as the Enſuring, Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Lumbring Deſigns, that there is a vaſt <hi>Bank</hi> of Mony lies unemployed; and yet the <hi>Nation</hi> never had a greater Trade, to employ Mony, never more ſhipping,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58680:15"/>never more Merchants, as will eaſily appear by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe Entries,</hi> both for Importation, and Exportation, with what they have been in former Years. And if any Perſon disbelieves the Truth of ſo well known matters of Fact, they muſt diſprove it, not only by ſaying Mony is ſcarce, but they muſt ſhew in Fact, by aſſigning how, where, and when, the Mony of the <hi>Nation</hi> is ſunk and drawn off <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> ſo as in that Senſe to make the Objection true, that the <hi>Nation is poor, i. e.</hi> that there is not actually ſo much Coin in <hi>England</hi> now this preſent Year 1683, as there was in 1653, when Mony, the <hi>Republicans</hi> ſay, was ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and every thing bore a Price. For though all the Coin in <hi>England</hi> were actually drawn into the City of <hi>London,</hi> and other trading, eſpecially Maritine Towns, ſo that a Man could not find a Croſs in the poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman's Pocket to keep the <hi>Devil</hi> out, yet muſt not the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be therefore ſaid to be the poorer, ſo long as the ſame Treaſure is actually in it, tho drawn into fewer Hands, which I take to be our preſent Caſe; Nay, I am of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>free Mintage</hi> of Mony, which is ſo beneficial and tempting to the Merchant, has brought more Mony into <hi>England,</hi> then the <hi>Eaſt India Trade</hi> hath carried out, and yet I believe there goes more Water by that Mill, then the Miller knows of.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Place therefore, I take it for granted, that the want of due <hi>Circulation</hi> of the Mony that is in the <hi>Nation,</hi> is the true Reaſon of the preſent ſcarcity of Mony. There is more Mony in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then the Trade of the <hi>Nation</hi> can Employ, that is moſt apparent: the Surpluſage lies ſtill in private Banks unimployed, but ready upon Occaſion to be iſſued out upon Purchaſes, Mortgages, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way which ſhall offer a conſiderable Advantage to the Owners. The lying ſtill of this Mony, together
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58680:15"/>with the conſtant drawing up of Money out of the <hi>Country</hi> to theſe little banks for the ſame purpoſes, ſtill drains the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> and keeps it bare. For in effect, there is little more Money circulates in the <hi>Inland Counties</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> than <hi>London</hi> and the other good Towns afford them for Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for the Mouth. The reſt of the <hi>Inland Trade,</hi> is upon the matter but barter and exchange of Commodity for Commodity, each <hi>Country</hi> mutually ſupplying themſelves in what they want from the other, ſo that here is ſtill part of the Running Caſh of the Country marching up into theſe little Petty-bag Offices, but <hi>veſtigia pauca retrorſum,</hi> no cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation from thence again.</p>
            <p>Thirdly therefore, I take it alſo for granted, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will be found to give Money a greater <hi>circulation,</hi> will make it more plentifull in the <hi>Nation;</hi> and the more Money does circulate, the more it will: for the <hi>Countries</hi> are not wanting in Commodities, but there is a want of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to advance the Rates of them; and therefore the more plentifull Money is, the better prices every thing gives; for all Markets riſe or fall in proportion to the number of Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and <hi>Chapmen</hi> are few or many in proportion to the plenty of Money which they have, and by conſequence therefore, till more Money does <hi>circulate,</hi> the Countryman will find little of it, and but indifferent Markets for his Commodities; and till Markets are better, Rents are not like to riſe; nor theſe little <hi>Bankers</hi> bring out their Hoards, till Lands riſe, and that they ſee hopes of advantage by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Purchaſers.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, the other three being granted, <hi>viz,</hi> That there is as great a ſtock of Money in the <hi>Nation,</hi> as ever; That the want of <hi>circulation</hi> makes it ſcarce; and, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will make more Money circulate, will make it more plentifull. I ſay, theſe being granted to be true in fact, as I cannot ſee any poſſibility of diſproving any one of them, the onely way to make more Money circulate, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58680:16"/>ſequence, to make it more plentifull, is by a liberal ſupply or the Occaſions and Expences of the Crown and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>This it may be at firſt view, eſpecially among the <hi>Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans,</hi> who cannot indure to hear of parting with Money to the <hi>King,</hi> may look like a pretty <hi>Court-project</hi> and <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox:</hi> but as I am no <hi>Courtier,</hi> nor have the remoteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency upon it, ſo I doubt not but both by Reaſon and Experience, ſo to ſupport my Aſſertion, as to make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that I am a true <hi>Countryman,</hi> not according to the <hi>Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> diſtinction of a <hi>Countryman,</hi> as oppoſite to a <hi>Courtier,</hi> but ſuch a <hi>Countryman,</hi> as would by ſupporting the Honour, Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Dignity of the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Court,</hi> alſo advance and improve the Intereſt of the <hi>Country.</hi> For let the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealthſmen</hi> ſay what they will, the Court and the Country are not two ſeparate Intereſts; and it will never be found that a Poor <hi>Exchequer</hi> made a Rich <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore firſt in point of Reaſon. In fact this is moſt evident, that the more Money the <hi>King</hi> hath, the more Money circulates through the whole <hi>Nation;</hi> and that except as before, what <hi>London</hi> and the good Towns of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> expend in Proviſion for the Mouth, the greateſt part of the Money that runs through the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> is what ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from the Branches of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Revenue;</hi> for the <hi>King</hi>'s Money is really current Coin in all ſenſes, it does not ruſt in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> it does not lie there for Purchaſes, Mortga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or other Bargains and Trade, but does continually iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue out again to defray die conſtant Charges and Expences of the Government, and is diſtributed into a multitude of Hands who have their dependence upon the <hi>Crown,</hi> and theſe again iſſue it out to ſupply their own Neceſſities to the trading part of the Kingdom, for the Native Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the <hi>Nation;</hi> ſo that it runs in a continual circle. Now the Revenue manifeſtly falling ſhort of the Expences of the Government, inſomuch, that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> has not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58680:16"/>onely been forced to retrench his Houſhold Expences, which occaſioned a great conſumption of our Native Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, and by conſequence the <hi>circulation</hi> of ſo much Money into the Country, but hath notwithſtanding been involved in a very great Debt; the ſupplying the <hi>Crown</hi> with ſuch Aids, as may enable the <hi>King</hi> to ſet up his <hi>Royal Tables,</hi> and Diſcharge his Debts, and not be forced to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve himſelf in new ones, as it would be highly honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> ſo it would be no more in effect, but the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> giving their Money with one hand to receive it again with the other, and the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off ſo much more Money to <hi>circulation</hi> throughout the <hi>Nation:</hi> And this again would likewiſe be abundantly recompenſed, both in our Foreign <hi>Traffick,</hi> and Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick <hi>Trade,</hi> as I will indeavour to make appear in its due place.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, the truth of this is moſt evident as from <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſo from <hi>Experience,</hi> which in my opinion is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the greateſt force and ſtrength: for many times Reaſon may be ſo brought to oppoſe Reaſon, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat of Arguments may appear ſo equal, as to leave the: Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſuſpence to which Party it ſhould incline to yield the <hi>Laurel</hi> of <hi>Truth and Victory;</hi> but though one cannot poſſibly ſee into every minute Circumſtance and the little concatenations of Cauſes and Effects, eſpecially where the number of them renders it intricate, ſo as to be able to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into the abſtruce and intangled reaſons of things, which like a ruffled skain of Silk may be difficult to be wound up to a bottom; yet if conſtant <hi>Experience</hi> ſhews, that thus it hath always been in ſuch and ſuch Caſes, then it is a very ſound Argument; that thus it will be again; and that certainly there is a true reaſon why it ſhould be ſo, though poſſibly it be too intricate to be drawn into a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration:</hi> though for my own particular, this point of the <hi>circulation</hi> of Money before diſcourſed of, ſeems ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58680:17"/>as to be undeniably the true foundation of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Experience</hi> in matter of fact.</p>
            <p>We will not travel out of our <hi>Kenn</hi> in this particular, though we might run as high as <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi>'s golden Reign, which we have been told was as plentifull in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as it was in Glory; the true reaſon whereof was that She was never denied any Money by her Subjects for the ſupport of the Government; though ſometimes ſhe rejected the <hi>Money Bills</hi> when the <hi>Golden Hook</hi> went a fiſhing for <hi>Royal Prerogative.</hi> But to come nearer home, it is in the Mouths of the <hi>Countryman</hi> and <hi>Citizen,</hi> and hath been main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improved and inſiſted upon by the <hi>Faction,</hi> to beget in them a good opinion of their <hi>Commonwealth Cauſe,</hi> and to put them out of conceit with <hi>Kingly</hi> Government, <hi>That Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was never more plentifull in this Nation, than during the times of the late <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi> The <hi>Fact</hi> is plain, though the <hi>Reaſon</hi> is not ſo to the many; but this will unriddle the Matter. For it is evident that the Trade of the <hi>Nation</hi> was nothing ſo conſiderable then as now; and the loſſes at Sea were extraordinary, it being computed that the <hi>Nation</hi> loſt during the War with <hi>Spain</hi> above 300 Sail of Ships beſides their Goods. But the true reaſon was this, thoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> raiſed what <hi>Taxes</hi> they pleaſed upon the <hi>Nation,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly above double the <hi>King</hi>'s preſent Revenue yearly, and many times treble; and there being a neceſſity for the defence of their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations</hi> to keep up great <hi>Fleets</hi> at Sea, and <hi>Forces</hi> at Land, the payment of theſe, and the charges they were at to keep themſelves in, and the <hi>King</hi> out of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of theſe <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> obliged them to iſſue out that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which came in upon the <hi>Aſſeſſments, Exciſe, Cuſtoms, Crown</hi> and <hi>Church-lands, Sequeſtrations,</hi> and other <hi>Funds,</hi> for the defraying of their Charges; by which means, there was double and treble the quantity of the <hi>King</hi>'s Revenue, which conſtantly <hi>circulated</hi> through the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> by reaſon whereof Money was made plentifull, and all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58680:17"/>bearing a conſiderable rate, Lands let at good pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thoſe heavy and illegal <hi>Taxes</hi> were the leſs felt. And ſure it is a very hard Caſe, that the <hi>Nation</hi> receiving a benefit by it too, they ſhould be unwilling to aſſiſt their Lawfull <hi>King,</hi> ſince they could ſo tamely ſubmit to do it to thoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to come a little nearer, let it be inſpected, and it will be found true, ſince his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s happy Return, that Money was never more plentifull, nor Lands let better, than when by reaſon of the free ſupplies which the <hi>Loyal Long-parliament</hi> gave him, the <hi>circulation</hi> of the Crown-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue ran briskly through the <hi>Nation.</hi> And on the other hand, that Money hath never been ſo ſcarce within the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Man, as for theſe laſt ſix or ſeven years that the <hi>Conſpiratours</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> getting into the Houſe of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> ſtopped the Money-ſprings, according to the advice and project of the E. of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Achitophel,</hi> whoſe deviliſh Counſel this was; and though not in it ſelf treaſonable, yet was by him, and his <hi>Traiterous</hi> Adherents, deſigned as one principal Way and Means, to enable them to accompliſh their Execrable <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> ſo miraculouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, by diſabling the <hi>King</hi> and his Friends, and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Government of the Power to oppoſe them in caſe they had proceeded to actual <hi>Hoſtilities</hi> and <hi>Inſurrections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, according to my promiſe, I muſt anſwer the obvious <hi>Objection</hi> which the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and People of better rank in the Nation will certainly make to this that hath been ſaid; they know their Rents are fallen, their Lands every day thrown into their hands, and that they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, for want of <hi>Tenants,</hi> to turn <hi>Farmers</hi> themſelves, and to ſtock and employ their own Eſtates. All this is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, and I know it experimentally my ſelf. Now will they ſay, This would be very hard upon us, to pay the ſame <hi>Rates</hi> and <hi>Taxes</hi> as formerly, when our <hi>Eſtates</hi> are leſſened a third part of their yearly value.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58680:18"/>
            <p>To this I anſwer. Firſt, that admitting what before hath been ſaid to be true, and till it is diſproved by ſtronger rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than that upon which it ſtands, it ought to be ſo eſteemed, I know no way to raiſe and increaſe their <hi>Rents</hi> in probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity like this; for upon the <hi>circulation</hi> of more Money, it muſt certainly be more plentifull, and all thoſe little <hi>Hoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Bankers</hi> will be obliged to let ſome part of theirs <hi>circulate,</hi> who now keep it up, and Money becoming more plentifull, all <hi>Country Commodities</hi> will advance in their price; the riſing of Country Commodities will enable and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <hi>Tenants</hi> to hire Lands, and will advance their Rents: So that upon the matter, the Money granted to the <hi>Crown,</hi> is but the beſt way of putting out ſome part of a Man's Eſtate, for die improvement of the reſt; and like ſowing <hi>Sain-foin,</hi> or <hi>Clover,</hi> which from three or four Shillings <hi>per</hi> Acre, will raiſe the Land to double or treble the value: And if there were nothing elſe in it, the <hi>Experiment</hi> is not ſo chargeable, but that it is worth the <hi>Nations</hi> trying; and I dare preſume to ſay, there is ſcarcely that <hi>Gentleman</hi> of Eſtate in <hi>England,</hi> but would upon as ſlender Inducements, venture as great a proportion as his part of any <hi>Royal Aid</hi> yet granted has amounted to, for the improment of his Eſtate; And at the worſt, ſhould it not ſucceed, yet the <hi>Nation</hi> has but done their duty to the <hi>King</hi> and themſelves in ſupplying the Occaſions of the Government, by parting with ſome part of their Eſtates in order to the ſecuring the Remainder from Foreign Force, or Domeſtick <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> ſo that at moſt it is but ſo much Money to inſure the <hi>Kingdom</hi> from the devouring Flames of a Civil or Foreign War. But if it ſhould ſucceed, as I cannot ſee how it can doe otherwiſe, it muſt make the <hi>King</hi> the greateſt <hi>Prince,</hi> and the <hi>Nation</hi> the richeſt People in the World.</p>
            <p>For, beſides the advantage and ſecurity we reap by ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the Government to protect us in all our juſt and legal Rights at home, againſt the Machinations of <hi>Factious Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58680:18"/>and <hi>Commonwealthſmen,</hi> this will give extraordinary encouragement and countenance to our Foreign Commerce, which is of mighty influence to the Inland Trade, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthening the <hi>Nation</hi> of the ſurpluſage of its <hi>Native Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities;</hi> for how deſirous ſoever any of our Covetous or Ambitious <hi>Neighbours</hi> may be to ſpoil our Markets, or rob us of our <hi>Trade,</hi> they will difficultly be perſuaded to break with us, or come to blows for it, when they ſhall ſee the Crown of <hi>England</hi> in capacity, by ſtrong and powerfull <hi>Fleets,</hi> to give Laws to the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and to redreſs the wrongs and injuries done or offered to our <hi>Merchants,</hi> though in the remoteſt corners of the <hi>Earth.</hi> Nay, it is more than poſſible, that the Strength, Riches and Reputation of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> may thereby come to be ſo advanced, as to render it the great <hi>Emporium</hi> and Exchange of the World.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, I anſwer, that for my own particular, I am for eaſing the Land as much as is poſſible, and think thoſe <hi>Impoſitions</hi> the beſt, which grow and ariſe upon ſuch things as are leaſt felt, ſuch as the duty upon Liquours, where the burthen is born by ſo many and in ſuch ſmall proportions, that it is ſcarcely felt by ſingle perſons. And poſſibly it would not hurt the <hi>Nation,</hi> by ſome <hi>Impoſition,</hi> to reſtrain the exceſſive luxuriance of buildings near the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which certainly make the <hi>Nation</hi> weak and <hi>Riketty,</hi> and depopulate the Country; and by withdrawing ſo many hands from Husbandry and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, in the ſeveral <hi>Counties</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> make Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants ſcarce and Rents fall.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, I am clearly for ſetting the Saddle upon the right Horſe; and ſince the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have occaſioned more than common neceſſity for the ſupporting the Crown, and ſecuring the Government againſt their Attempts, to oblige them to bear the greateſt part of that Charge. We have had many boaſts from them of late years, how conſiderable they are for number and wealth: now ſince they have by their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58680:19"/>repeated indeavours made it viſible, that they would miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploy their Strength and Riches, to the ſubverſion of the preſent Government, there is all the reaſon in the world, and their own reaſon too, when they had the power, that they ſhould bear the Charges, which they have created; and that the honeſt and <hi>Loyal Party</hi> ſhould not be obliged to ſuffer in their Eſtates, to ſecure the <hi>King</hi> and Government againſt their diſturbances and wicked attempts.</p>
            <p>But beſides, it is not onely reaſonable, and the practice of all Governments, but marvellous juſt too. They cannot complain of <hi>Adonibezeck</hi>'s Law, eſpecially ſince the return will be but to pare their Nails, in requital of their cutting off the Thumbs, nay the Hands and Heads of the <hi>Royal Party.</hi> They have had their day, and took all, it is but juſt the <hi>Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> ſhould have theirs too, and take ſome. The Riches they value themſelves ſo much upon, what are they, but the ſpoils of the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> when they grew rich and great by oppreſſing, ſequeſtring, taxing and plundring the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Loyal Party?</hi> For when they had the poor <hi>Royaliſts</hi> under their power, they made them defray the greateſt part of the Charges of the <hi>Nation</hi> out of their Eſtates; and ſurely they can have no reaſon to complain, if they receive ſome part of the meaſure, which they then called the higheſt Juſtice, and did ſo liberally diſpenſe to others. And truly it is but a Pig of their own Sow, the Child of their own <hi>Politicks;</hi> for if they can believe it ſo high a point of <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> to keep the <hi>King</hi> from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that ſo he might not be able to traverſe their Deſigns, or hinder their Attempts; the ſame and far greater <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> lies againſt them, not to permit them to be Maſters of ſo much Money, as to be able therewith to hurt the <hi>King,</hi> or diſturb the Government. And truly it will be a great kindneſs to them to diſable them from doing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; like the taking of a Sword out of a Madman's hand for fear he ſhould kill himſelf, or ſome other with it.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58680:19"/>and ſeeing they cannot make a better uſe of it, 'tis the beſt way of employing their <hi>Talent</hi> for them, to the publick good and ſafety of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and thereby prevent their running to the <hi>Gallows</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> too, and loſing all.</p>
            <p>I know Mr. <hi>Trimmer</hi> will preſently be upon my bones, with the danger of exaſperating a <hi>Party</hi> ſo conſiderable as the <hi>Diſſenting Brotherhood</hi> would have us upon occaſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they are, though I fancy if every <hi>Conventicler</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were to be taxed three ſhillings to my one, they would all like the <hi>Scotch man</hi> cry, <hi>I'ſe eat Peark,</hi> and the <hi>Porridg</hi> too of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and dwindle into a very pitiful <hi>Muſter-Roll;</hi> but by Mr. <hi>Trimmer</hi>'s favour, and for all his fear of running them upon Extremities, they are mightily out of love with Hemp and wry Faces; and I believe they are now already as mad as Malice and Deſpair can make them, but as curſt as they are, they know their Horns are as ſhort. And if they be ſo dangerous when they are angry, it is the more neceſſary, to abate their ſtrength; for my life for yours, Mr. <hi>Trimmer,</hi> if they want money, they will not want <hi>wit</hi> in their <hi>anger;</hi> and moſt certainly, they who are ſo apt to be angry, and whoſe anger is capable of tranſporting them to ſuch Extremities, as to flie in the face of the Government, ought like <hi>Maſtiffs</hi> and <hi>Bull Doggs,</hi> to be well muzzled, that they may not bite, though they bark never ſo fiercely. And if this be their Temper, that they have not duty enough for God and the King, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them againſt Rebellion, it is moſt ſure, that they will be no longer quiet or honeſt, than they are kept ſo by want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opportunity and ſtrength to ſhew their anger, and flie to Extremities. Fear only reſtrains them, Love and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs never did, never will. And ſo long as they have Power they will be dangerous; let us take that from them, and then let Mr. <hi>Trimmer</hi> and his <hi>Exaſperado</hi>'s do their worſt.</p>
            <p>But let the wayes of raiſing be never ſo juſt and neceſſary,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58680:20"/>eaſie and advantageous for the ſupport, ſafety and Dignity of the Government, how we ſhall come by this Mony will be the next inquiry? Truly I know no other way but by a Loyal and brave <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi> And for my own particular, I cannot ſee the leaſt Cloud to darken the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, but that whenever the <hi>King</hi> ſhall pleaſe to call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> the next <hi>Elections</hi> will generally fall upon ſuch Worthy and Loyal <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> as will effectually do the buſineſs of the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Nation.</hi> And the <hi>Faction</hi> have by their late actions, and the diſcovery of their Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> laid themſelves and their wicked Intentions ſo open, and expoſed to the deteſtation of the whole World, that I cannot conceive in any future <hi>Parliament,</hi> there ſhould be found in any <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſo much wanting to his own Reputation, as to appear a <hi>Patron</hi> or Advocate for ſuch a ſort of People as ſtand convicted of ill Deſigns againſt the Government, as the <hi>Mony-oppoſers</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters</hi> do. And though poſſibly ſome few of the ſame Perſons with their Old Principles, may get again into the <hi>Commons Houſe,</hi> yet I am apt to think, they will be very cautious of their Words, ſince it may be the turn of the <hi>Loyal Party</hi> too <hi>to call to the Barr,</hi> and purge the Houſe of <hi>Aſſociators, Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners,</hi> the <hi>Men of Shaftsbury,</hi> the <hi>Grey Coats</hi> and <hi>Monmouth Caps.</hi> It may happen, that the <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Voters</hi> of <hi>Eighty,</hi> may be as low in Reputation in the Opinion of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and all honeſt and <hi>Loyal</hi> Men out of it, as thoſe of 40 and 41; and that ſome perſons who uſed to be liberal <hi>Speakers</hi> heretofore, may ſit there as if they were in the School of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> with their Fingers, either in, or, upon their Mouths, a better way to deſerve the Title of the Wiſdom of the <hi>Nation,</hi> which they have ſo much affected, than by making ſuch Speeches as will not be heard with <hi>Patience,</hi> nor go off with <hi>Impunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince before the <hi>Elections</hi> of the late <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the <hi>Faction</hi> uſed luſtily to beſtir themſelves to give aim, it is but one good turn for another, if we pay them in their own
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58680:20"/>Coin. For their <hi>Liſt of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous Votes,</hi> which they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently Printed, purpoſely to expoſe ſo many Worthy and Loyal <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to the contempt and hatred of the People; and to hinder them from being Elected into future <hi>Parliaments,</hi> it were eaſie to repay them with a <hi>Liſt of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Contradicente</hi>'s, That the <hi>King</hi> ſhould neither have Mony nor Credit to take up any upon the Reputation of his Revenue; It were eaſie to give a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of ſuch as were Zealous, by the <hi>Bill of Excluſion,</hi> to turn the <hi>Monarchy</hi> from an <hi>Hereditary</hi> and Lineal Deſcent, into an <hi>El ctive Parliamentary Title,</hi> and for backing this with an <hi>Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to enable the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to take up Arms under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſecuring his Majeſties Perſon, to deſtroy both Him and the Government; according to the Printed Vote of <hi>Dec.</hi> 15. 1680. When it was Reſolved, <hi>&amp;c. That a Bill be brought in for an Aſſociation of all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">By which was alwayes in the Cant of the Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, underſtood <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Proteſtant Subjects, for the ſafety of his Majeſties Perſon, the Defence of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, the Preſervation of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Proteſtant Subjects, againſt all</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">That word is well expounded in the Trial of the Conſpirators.</note> 
               <hi>Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Oppoſitions</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Not excepting the King.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoever, and for preventing the Duke of</hi> York, <hi>or any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt from ſucceeding to the Crown.</hi> It were eaſie to mark every individual perſon who was then buſie in promoting the <hi>Common-Wealth Deſign,</hi> ſome of which as <hi>Trenchard, Booth, Hamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> and the late L. <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> are now ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and ſome of them rewarded according to their Traiterous Practices. But their Names as well as Actions, are publick enough in the Printed Votes, and the <hi>Nation</hi> knows them to a man, and therefore, I need not waſte Paper to repeat them.</p>
            <p>But in regard I think it is the Duty of every good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject who loves the <hi>King,</hi> and wiſhes well to <hi>England,</hi> to contribute all that lies in his Power, that ſuch <hi>Gentlemen</hi> may be choſen, and ſent to repreſent them in the next
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58680:21"/>
               <hi>Parliament,</hi> as may comport themſelves within the bounds of Duty and affectionate Loyalty to the <hi>King,</hi> ſuch as will purſue the true intereſt of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> by ſecuring the Government and Peace of both Church and State, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think it amiſs to offer ſome Qualifications, requiſite to recommend ſuch Perſons to the Conſiderations of the Freeholders and Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> as may ſpeak them fit for that great Truſt and Honour.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>firſt negatively,</hi> No ſuch Perſons as have been either open or ſecret favourers of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and courted by them. Such of all men are moſt unfit; for it is moſt certain that no good can be expected from them, who are imbarqued in an intereſt <hi>diametrically</hi> oppoſite to the Church and Crown, as all the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in <hi>England</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly are; and it is as certain, that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> never beſtow their Regards but upon ſuch as favour them, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver indeavour to ſet up any perſon to be a Member of the <hi>Commons Houſe,</hi> but in expectancy, and upon aſſurance from them, that they will be ſerviceable to their Cauſe and Intereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> No ſuch Perſons, nor their Deſcendants as have been actually ingaged in the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> who were them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or whoſe Anceſtors were poſſeſſed of any part of the Crown or Church Lands. For <hi>Principles</hi> and averſion do deſcend to <hi>Poſterity;</hi> and for thoſe who were actors in the War, and ſharers of the Booty, they are not to be truſted, unleſs they have given eminent teſtimonies of their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; otherwiſe aſſuredly they retain the ſame <hi>Antimonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical</hi> Principles, which overthrew the Government before; they cannot forget the ſweetneſs of that <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> which they then exerciſed, when a <hi>Colonel</hi> or a <hi>Captain</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer'd over a whole <hi>Country;</hi> they look upon themſelves as injured in the loſs of thoſe fair Eſtates, of which in the times of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> they were the fooliſh purchaſers and unjuſt poſſeſſors, and upon all theſe accounts will not only do no good, but all the hurt they can, in hopes if the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58680:21"/>were but again overturned, they might come into their Eſtates and Power again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> No ſuch as have been buſie <hi>ſticklers,</hi> againſt granting Money, no <hi>Excluſioners, Aſſociators,</hi> ſpreaders of jealouſies of the Deſigns of the Government to introduce <hi>Popery, ſlavery,</hi> and ſuch abominable Calumnies againſt the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters;</hi> for all ſuch if they have not been actually ingaged, though it may be ſo ſecretly as to eſcape diſcovery, in the late <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> yet gave countenance and encouragement to the <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> and though the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret was not plainly communicated to them, yet were ſuch as the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> aſſured themſelves, would certainly joyn them upon ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> No ſuch as have been Zealous promoters of branding, or <hi>Tophamizing</hi> the beſt and moſt Loyal of his <hi>Maj ſties</hi> Subjects, as betrayers of the <hi>Nation,</hi> Enemies to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> favourers of <hi>Popery;</hi> no ſuch as have been promoters of real <hi>Arbitrary</hi> impriſoning and puniſhing ſuch of his Majeſties good Subjects, as in their ſeveral ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only did their Duty and diſcharged their <hi>Conſciences</hi> in diſcountenancing tumultuary <hi>Petitioning,</hi> and in oppoſing the violent courſes and proceedings of the <hi>Faction.</hi> For ſuch Men are very unlikely to ſecure our Liberty and Property, who have been ſuch notorious invaders of them, and can never be true Friends to the Crown and Government, who have branded the moſt Loyal Subjects, with the infamous character of, Enemies to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> None of thoſe who have been for their being diſaffected, put out of the Commiſſion of the Peace, or Offices in the <hi>Militia,</hi> or diſcarded from places of Profit, Truſt and Honour in the Government, for they will think revenge better than Muſcadine and Eggs, and will ſtudy that more than to ſerve the <hi>Publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for an even half dozen, none of that wretched Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of <hi>Trimmers,</hi> thoſe <hi>Janus-faced Proteſtants,</hi> thoſe State <hi>Otters,</hi> neither Fiſh nor Fleſh nor good red Herring
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58680:22"/>Stateſmen, for it is a clear Caſe, He that is not with us, is againſt us, and theſe pretended moderate Men, are immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately falſe and rotten at Core, outſide Friends, inward and ſecret foes, and by far more dangerous than open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: like <hi>Joab</hi> they kiſs and ſtabb; theſe, if they can do no more, will keep the head of the <hi>Faction</hi> above Water: and in ſhort they are too like the <hi>Devil</hi> to be truſted, for like a true <hi>Trimmer,</hi> where he can do no hurt as a Devil, he will do it as an Angel, but they are eaſily known, the one, as they ſay, by his cloven foot, and the other by his cloven tongue.</p>
            <p>Put in the laſt place <hi>affirmatively,</hi> Such <hi>Gentlemen</hi> are fit for the Publick Honour to ſerve their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> as its Repreſentative in Parliament, who have either hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or in theſe later times of diſorder, manifeſted their ſteady Loyalty to the <hi>King,</hi> and hearty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Government eſtabliſhed in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> whoſe Reputations are not blemiſhed by any ſuſpicion of confederacy, intimacy, kindneſs, or Correſpondency ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſuch of the late <hi>Conſpirators</hi> as are convicted or fled from the Juſtice of the Laws; but who have given proofs of their fidelity to the Crown by oppoſing the <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For theſe are the Men of Honour and integrity, who equally deteſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Phanaticiſm, Pickering</hi>'s ſcrewed Gun, and <hi>Rumbolds</hi> unſcrewed Blunderbuſſes; who will really indeavour to ſecure the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and the <hi>Monarchy</hi> againſt their Enemies on both hands. Theſe and only ſuch are the Men that are the true <hi>Patriots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that will truſt the <hi>King,</hi> and therefore are fit to be truſted by the <hi>Country,</hi> who will not only according to the <hi>Mode</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> make a loud clamour and Bawling of the danger of the Proteſtant Religion and the <hi>Kings</hi> perſon, but apply ſuch effectual remedies, as may contribute to the real ſafety of both, who will not only ſcorn to be <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> but will inable the <hi>King</hi> upon occaſion to oppoſe the too near greatneſs of that Ambitious <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy;</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58680:22"/>and not like the Men of the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> cry out againſt <hi>French Penſioners</hi> and <hi>French Councils,</hi> and yet themſelves do the buſineſs of the <hi>French,</hi> by tying the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi>'s hands, and tying up the Purſe of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe weight is only able to ballance <hi>France;</hi> not amuſe and incenſe the People with diſmal ſtories of the danger of <hi>France,</hi> and at the ſame time by keeping up the diviſions of <hi>England</hi> augment thoſe dangers, and find the Government work enough to conſult and take care of its own ſecurity at home, ſo as neither to have Money nor leiſure enough to look after, or be able to prevent any dangers abroad: in a word the <hi>Nation</hi> muſt have a new houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> if a <hi>new Parliament,</hi> and a <hi>new Parliament</hi> if they expect any good, and Peace of ſettlement either in Church and State at home, or ſecurity and Honour abroad, and therefore by clear conſequence either not the <hi>Old Members</hi> with the <hi>Old Principles,</hi> or the <hi>Old Principles</hi> with <hi>New Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very probable however, that the <hi>Diſſenting Faction</hi> will not abandon all their hopes, but being ſtill in many places animated by the <hi>Principal</hi> Men of their <hi>Party,</hi> and led by their ill <hi>Deſtiny</hi> to pull down vengeance upon their own heads, it is poſſible they will ſtruggle hard in ſome <hi>Elections</hi> to over vote the <hi>Loyaliſts,</hi> and obtrude the ſame, or Men of the ſame leaven upon the <hi>Nation.</hi> Now though I know nothing that obliges me to give them good advice, but pure Compaſſion, yet I would deſire them to look before they leap; and if they have not forfeited all their ſhare of <hi>Common diſcretion,</hi> to ſee where their <hi>Intereſt</hi> lies. Every man that hath but a grain of ſence, will conſult his own advantage, and before he adventures upon any thing the conſequences whereof may be very great, conſider ſeriouſly of the matter, and make a computation of what gain or loſs it may be to him; and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they do not now in this conjuncture, they will no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be the <hi>ſober Party,</hi> but act like raſh, inconſiderable Bedlams, and men drunk with Rage and deſperation.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58680:23"/>
            <p>I would therefore as a true Friend, that would have them ſee the worſt of their Caſe, adviſe them firſt to look up and ſee what time of the day it is with them; for upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they will find that the <hi>Sun</hi> of their <hi>Hopes</hi> is juſt upon ſetting in a <hi>black Cloud</hi> of Eternal Night. They will find, that they have nothing in the World left to expect, unleſs ſome Miracles, to which they may truſt their <hi>Expiring Cauſe.</hi> They will find that the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> is grown, and will grow overy day ſtronger, and their Houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of God, every moment weaker. They will find, that the <hi>Nation</hi> is thoroughly awakened with the danger of Blood and Confuſion, in which the Leaders of their <hi>Faction</hi> had deſigned to involve it. And what can they now poſſibly hope for by oppoſing the Government, and the <hi>Loyal Party</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> by endeavouring to ſend diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Repreſentatives to the <hi>Parliament?</hi> there is ſcarcely a bare poſſibility, conſidering how many will every where for very ſhame fall off from them, as well as others out of fear or honeſty, that they ſhould gain a Majority in the <hi>Commons Houſe:</hi> and if they fail in that, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance which they have made, and the endeavours to oppoſe the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> will oblige them to inforce the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the <hi>Penal</hi> Laws againſt them, and to provide greater ſeverities for the future. For if they ſhall now dare to ſtruggle with the Government, and make diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, when they are under all the diſadvantages ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, it will ſhew that they are a People of ſuch <hi>deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> as well as <hi>dangerous Principles,</hi> that there cannot be too great Caution uſed, nor too great care taken, by the utmoſt ſeverity of Laws, and the due Execution of them, to take away their ſtrength, ſuppreſs them, and hinder the growth and progreſs of ſuch <hi>Principles,</hi> and numbers of Men, as in time may be fatal to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58680:23"/>
            <p>And were it poſſible, which truly they muſt be of very ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine tempers that can hope it, that the <hi>Faction</hi> ſhould get ſuch another <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> according to their wiſhes, yet what would they be the better for it, ſince there is no hopes of a <hi>Perpetual Seſſion?</hi> And becauſe they ſhall have an eaſie way how to compute what they may get for the future, I would deſire them to take Pen, Ink and Paper, and ſet down what they have got already by the former diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances of this nature which they have given the <hi>Nation.</hi> I am of opinion, when they have ſtated the matter, they may put all the gains in their Eyes, and whereas we commonly ſay, ſee ne'er the worſe, I fancy it will make them ſee much the better; ſee their folly and madneſs, and if they have any remainders of prudence or diſcretion, teach them to leave trading upon that <hi>New-found-land-bank</hi> of a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> where they will catch nothing but, <hi>had I Fiſh,</hi> and <hi>Poor John.</hi> There was a time when they had ſome hopes, they can have none now; for moſt certainly the <hi>Nation</hi> will never be at reſt, till it hath by repeated trials and changes purged off this <hi>old Commonwealth Scurvy,</hi> and got a ſound new Repreſentative Body; and till it comes to that period, the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who are the onely hinderers and oppoſers of it, muſt expect to be treated by the Laws and Government, as the enemies of the peace and happineſs, the quiet and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Government may be very tender and unwilling to proceed to extremities of ſeverity; but when it ſhall appear that compaſſion to the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> and the Enemies of the Government, is cruelty to it ſelf and to all the <hi>Loyaliſts</hi> its true Friends, the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have little reaſon to promiſe themſelves impunity, or that the Government will run the hazzard of diſobliging Friends, and turning them into Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in hopes of making their <hi>Old Enemies, New Friends.</hi> And the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> cannot take any courſe more effectual, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the whole <hi>Nation</hi> of the neceſſity of ſuch ſevere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedures
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58680:24"/>againſt them, than by making ſuch oppoſition to the peace and ſettlement of it, by ſending or indeavouring to ſend ill men to the <hi>Repreſentative Body:</hi> And they may aſſure themſelves, that particular notice will be taken in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place of all ſuch <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to a man as make it their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to ſet up, or vote for ill Men, and they will be ſure to be remembred upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>Whereas would they be contented with the liberty and indulgence which the Laws allow them, which truly are very great, would they leave ſtickling, creating diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and exaſperating the <hi>Nation</hi> againſt them, they may reaſonably hope to enjoy the favours already allowed them, which otherwiſe they will alſo in the concluſion be ſure to loſe. But if they would hear reaſon, I would adviſe them to an intire ſubmiſſion to the Laws and Government in Church and State: this will be the beſt way of uniting <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> for them to unite with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> where they will infallibly learn two ſhort Leſſons, which will ſave their Purſes, their Perſons and their Souls, Truly to <hi>fear God,</hi> and <hi>honour the King.</hi> This is their indiſpenſible duty: This is their true intereſt: This would make them eaſie, the Government ſafe, and the Nation happy. And if they ſhall obſtinately perſiſt to oppoſe all theſe, they will declare themſelves open Enemies to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and muſt expect as a reward of their Actions, not onely the hatred of the <hi>Nation,</hi> but the ſeverity of ſuch puniſhments in this World, as are juſtly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to the common Enemies of <hi>Mankind</hi> and humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, but alſo that dreadfull <hi>Damnation</hi> hereafter, which the great Apoſtle, as an <hi>Oracle of God</hi> hath intailed upon all ſuch as reſiſt the Higher Powers; whoſe command to the contrary is abſolute, is peremptory, is univerſal, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> and that for <hi>Conſcience ſake; for the Powers that be are ordained of God,</hi> ſo that they who reſiſt the Higher Powers, reſiſt God himſelf, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58680:24"/>what the iſſue of ſuch a Combat will prove, I need not tell them, but heartily wiſh they may by repentance eſcape the dreadfull end of thoſe men, who for ſpeaking evil of Dignities and deſpiſing Dominions, muſt certainly periſh in the gainſaying of <hi>Corah,</hi> that <hi>Primitive Diſſenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but a few words more to add, and thoſe are to the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> that they would not be leſs aſſiduous to ſupport the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than the <hi>Conſpiratours</hi> and <hi>Faction</hi> have been to ſubvert it: and ſince the happy turn of their Affairs doth in ſo great a meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the good conſtitution of their <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will not be wanting to themſelves, either in diligence or caution, to elect and ſend ſuch Men to die <hi>Commons Houſe</hi> as may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the juſt Ends of all good <hi>Parliaments;</hi> which have ever been called to conſult for the common good of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and to tender to the <hi>Royal Aſſent</hi> ſuch Bills to be paſſed into Laws, as might promote the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſecure the Government, and ſupport the Crown, by granting ſuch aids of Money as may inable the <hi>King</hi> to protect his <hi>Subjects,</hi> make good his <hi>Alliances,</hi> aſſiſt his <hi>Friends</hi> and ſubdue his <hi>Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have in all my obſervation, ever taken notice, that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have outdone the <hi>Loyaliſts</hi> in their diligence; they would go through fire and water to a publick Election, and at a <hi>Common Hall</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> or a <hi>County Court</hi> in the <hi>Country</hi> for Elections, the whole Party to a man be preſent. What will doe their buſineſs, will certainly doe ours; and I am confident, generally ſpeaking, it is impoſſible they ſhould overvote the <hi>Royal Party,</hi> if they could but be perſuaded with the ſame zeal to ſtand up for the true Intereſt of the <hi>Nation,</hi> as the other do for that of the <hi>Faction.</hi> But above all the <hi>Freeholders</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> have the moſt reaſon, both by themſelves, and the united Intereſt of the <hi>Church Party,</hi> to promote good <hi>Elections;</hi> for they are not onely the particular <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Butt</hi> of the <hi>Factions</hi> hatred, but in the late indeavours and Bills for regulating Elections, the deſign was laid, to take away the Votes of all the leſſer <hi>Freeholders</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially to deveſt the <hi>Clergy</hi> of their ancient Free Liberties in that particular: and if that Project had ſucceeded, they would have ſeen ſuch Perſons made <hi>Electours,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Elected,</hi> as would quickly have eaſed them of their <hi>Benefices</hi> as well as <hi>Voices;</hi> ſince they might almoſt with the ſame juſtice take away the one as the other. I know not by what artifices in many places ſeveral of the <hi>Clergy</hi> have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to go along with the <hi>Faction,</hi> but I am aſſured, that either they did not underſtand their own <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or if they did, they had little regard either to that, or the Duty which they owe to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> or to their <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> all which are obligations which do more
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58680:25"/>ſtrongly bind them to be true and <hi>Loyal,</hi> than any other rank of men whatſoever.</p>
            <p>The impending <hi>Rupture</hi> between the two Crowns of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> will neceſſarily draw in <hi>England,</hi> both upon the account of ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation by Articles of Treaty, and by the true Intereſt of the <hi>Nation,</hi> which is to keep the Balance even, and to prevent <hi>France</hi> from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too great a Neighbour by the acceſſion of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by Conqueſt, to that <hi>Crown.</hi> And the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will ſtand in need of the aſſiſtence of his Loyal Subjects, to make him the more able to accommodate that matter, either as a <hi>Party,</hi> or a <hi>Mediatour,</hi> or both; ſo as that <hi>England</hi> may be thereby ſecured from the danger of <hi>France.</hi> This therefore, will be a <hi>Critical juncture,</hi> wherein the <hi>King</hi> will try who are really his Friends, and who will ſtand by him and the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> in ſending ſuch <hi>Gentlemen</hi> for their Repreſentatives to the <hi>Commons Houſe,</hi> as may aſſiſt him effectually, both with their Counſels, and, with Supplies ſufficient to go through with that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Affair, to die preſent honour, and future ſecurity of the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> For <hi>England</hi> may be aſſured, that what <hi>France</hi> gains in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, England</hi> loſeth; and that the <hi>Maritim Provinces</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> will not be long able to avoid ſubmitting to the Yoke, if once <hi>Flanders</hi> be loſt. And what would become of our <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Navigation,</hi> if that Crown, already very potent at Sea, were by ſo much Shipping, and ſo many able Seamen, inabled to contraſt with us the Sovereignty of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> which they now difficultly acknowledge, it is eaſie to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee. And moſt aſſuredly it is better and more eaſie to prevent ſo great a miſchief, than to diſintangle our ſelves after having fallen into it. And in ſhort, let <hi>England</hi> be aſſured, that if ſhe tamely ſuffer <hi>Flanders</hi> to be loſt, ſhe can expect no other favour from <hi>France,</hi> than what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> was to have had from <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> to be the laſt of her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that is to be devoured.</p>
            <p>To conclude, be it Peace, or, be it War, whether we expect to enjoy quiet at home, or honour abroad, ſecurity from Domeſtick or Foreign Dangers, encreaſe of Trade, or plenty of Money, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can make this <hi>Nation</hi> happy and the <hi>Monarchy</hi> great, all will in a very large meaſure be found to depend upon what hath been ſaid in theſe few Sheets; which are therefore earneſtly recommended to the conſideration of all true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> of what Names of Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſoever, in hopes, that they will all unanimouſly indeavour to promote the Glory of <hi>God,</hi> the Honour and Safety of the <hi>King,</hi> and the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> which is and ought to be not onely of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, but of all Mens Actions and Indeavours, the Aim, the Scope,</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58680:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
